Richard Coke papers, Inclusive: 1828-1964, undated, Bulk: 1852-1957, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Richard Coke papers
Inclusive: 1828-1964, undated, Bulk: 1852-1957, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
66
Coke, Richard
2 document boxes and 1 oversized box.
The Richard Coke papers consist of correspondence, legal, financial, literary, and scrapbook manuscripts, plus photographs of former Texas governor Richard Coke.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Richard Coke was born in 1829 March 13 near Williamsburg, Virginia, to John and Eliza Hankins Coke. He apparently received good primary education, since he entered William and Mary College in 1843, graduating in 1848 with a law degree. In 1850 he moved to Waco, Texas, perhaps looking for a place on the frontier that he could use his skills as a lawyer. His law business did very well, and he became known for his abilities in both civil and criminal law cases. Richard married Waco girl Mary Evans Horne in 1852. Though the couple had four children, none of them lived to adulthood. Several letters, receipts, and legal forms are in the collection from these early years of Coke’s life.
Richard Coke’s political career began in 1859 when he was appointed by Texas governor Hardin R. Runnels to a commission that decided the Comanche Indians must be removed from Texas. Coke was a delegate to the Texas Secession Convention, voting for secession. During the American Civil War, he was captain of Company K, 15th Texas Infantry, under Colonel Joseph Warren Speight. As part of the 15th Texas, Coke fought in the Trans-Mississippi, including Arkansas, Louisiana, and Texas, and was wounded at the Battle of Bayou Bourbeau in 1863 November 3. With the war over, Coke was appointed judge of the Texas 19th Judicial District by Reconstruction Governor A.J. Hamilton. In 1866 Richard Coke was elected as justice of the state supreme court, but was removed by General Philip H. Sheridan when the Radical Republican Congress divided the South into military-controlled districts in 1867. Coke continued his efforts to influence Texas political life, and was elected as the first post-war Democratic governor of Texas in 1873 by over forty thousand votes. His victory was bitterly contested by the state Republican Party, the state supreme court, and outgoing Governor Edmund J. Davis, but he took office in 1874 January with popular majority backing. The collection\ contains several documents written during the Civil War, as well as several certificates from right after the war.
As governor, Richard Coke pushed for undoing many of programs adopted during Republican rule of Texas. He cut spending by reducing funding for state asylums, state printing, and decentralizing the school system, but the savings were wiped out by increasing the military presence on the Texas-Mexico border and guarding the frontier from Comanche and Kiowa trying to regain their land and way of life. As part of his rollback of Republican programs, Coke and the Democratic-controlled Congress passed a new state constitution. Voters expressed their approval of his actions by reelecting Richard Coke as governor in 1876, but he resigned in 1877 upon his election as United States senator. There are almost no manuscripts directly from Coke’s time as governor, though several letters and other documents date from his years in the United States senate.
Coke’s career in the United States senate lasted for seventeen years. During that time, he earned a reputation as an informed senator who generally voted in line with other Southern Democrats. He opposed federal aid to schools, tariffs to protect domestic manufacturing, suspending silver coinage, and providing federal army protection to elections threatened by intimidation. Coke supported the Bland-Allison Act of 1878 and the Interstate Commerce Act of 1887. He did not run for reelection in 1894.
After retirement from political life, Richard Coke did some farming along the Brazos River. However, he enjoyed retirement for only three years before he died at his home in Waco in 1897 May 14. Luminaries such as the governor of Texas at the time were pallbearers during his funeral at Oakwood Cemetery, Waco. Richard Coke is remembered today for his election as the first post-Civil War Democratic governor of Texas.
Much of the collection was gathered by the McCelvey family, especially by Mary Elizabeth “Honey” Horne McCelvey, who was the niece of Richard Coke’s wife Mary Evans Horne Coke. Mary Horne McCelvey apparently lived with Richard and Mary Coke during the last six years of Richard’s life, and eventually inherited many of his historical manuscripts.
Scope and Content
The Richard Coke papers begin in 1828 and ends in 1964. Records include correspondence, legal and financial documents, literary productions, and photographic materials. The scrapbooks series is the largest in the collection. The legal series contains many early documents, some dating from the Republic of Texas and earlier.
Richard Coke, resident of Waco, Texas, and state governor, legislature, and lawyer, was one of the most influential political figures in Texas during the late 1800s. His papers held by The Texas
Collection include letters, legal records, financial documents, literary productions, scrapbook materials, and photographs. This small but diverse collection reflects the many activities of Richard Coke on the local and state political stage.
Much of the scrapbooks concern old Waco families and the Horne family, and not Richard Coke directly. Some of the scrapbook materials are from the Horne family during the mid-1900.
The land deeds within the Legal Series pertain include many early deeds from McLennan County and the surrounding area. It is thought that Richard Coke was called in as a lawyer to settle disputes about the deeds, such as boundary disagreements.
Arrangement
Though an unusually large amount of some documentation exists for this collection, there was little organization and no finding aid available. Several inventories existed before this finding aid.
Currently, the Richard Coke papers are arranged in six series: I. Correspondence, II. Legal Documents, III. Financial Documents, IV. Literary Productions, V. Scrapbook Materials, and VI. Photographic Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 66. Acquired 1976-03-18
Related Resources
Related collection materials
Richard Coke Scrapbook, 1864-1912, Dolph Briscoe Center of American History, The University of Texas at Austin.
Texas Governor Richard Coke Records. Archives and Information Services Division, Texas State Library and Archives Commission.
Related references
Duncan, Merle Mears. “The Death of Senator Coke.” The Southwestern Historical Quarterly 63, 3 (1960 January): 385-403.
Duncan, Merle Mears and Richard Coke. “An 1890 Richard Coke Letter.” The Southwestern Historical Quarterly 66, 1 (1962 July): 68-72.
Moneyhon, Carl H. “Edmund J. Davis in the Coke-Davis Election Dispute of 1874: A Reassessment of Character.” The Southwestern Historical Quarterly 100, 2 (1996 October): 130-151.
Payne, Jr., John W. “Coke, Richard.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2011 November 30.
Roberts, Oscar Walter. “Richard Coke on Constitution-Making.” The Southwestern Historical Quarterly 78, 1 (1974 July): 69-75.
Texas Historical Commission. “McCelvey, Dr. John S. and Mary, House.” Texas Historic Sites Atlas. Accessed 2011 December 1.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Coke, Richard, 1829-1897.
Places
Texas -- Photographs.; Texas -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950.
Subjects
Land Deed -- Texas; Lawyers -- Texas.; Legislators -- Texas.
Genres
Certificates.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches.
- Correspondence, 1848-1910; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains correspondence to and from Richard Coke during most of his life. A letter during the American Civil War addresses him as captain. Other letters date from his years in the United States Senate.
  - Correspondence, 1848-1878 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1882-1910 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Legal Documents, 1828-1885, undated; 2
  This series contains general legal documents and land deeds dating from before the Republic of Texas. One of the land deeds was to Asa Hoxey.
  - General, 1860-1885 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Land Deeds, 1828-1838 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Land Deeds, 1848-1852 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Land Deeds, 1852 February-May (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Land Deeds, 1853-1854 April (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Land Deeds (1 of 2), 1854 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Land Deeds (2 of 2), 1854 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Land Deeds, 1854 November-1855 October (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Land Deeds, 1857-1859 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Land Deeds, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Land Deeds, 1861-1865, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Financial Documents, 1848-1852, undated; 3
  This series contains receipts for various monetary amounts. One is made out to the Republic of Texas treasurer Henry Smith, for a firm in New Orleans to pay one thousand dollars upon receipt of the bill.
  - General, 1848-1852, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Literary Productions, 1865-1957, undated; 4
  This series contains various speeches, genealogy materials, clippings, and certificates. Richard Coke gave the speeches while he was a United States senator. The certificates are from the end of the American Civil War, made out by Texas governor A.J. Hamilton to Richard Coke.
  - General, 1865-1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Genealogy, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Speeches, 1878-1880 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Speeches, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Speeches, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Clippings, 1897-1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Clippings (1 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Clippings (2 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Certificate, 1865 (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 3)
  - Certificate, 1866 (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 4)
  - Certificate, undated (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 5)
- Scrapbook Materials, 1866-1964, undated; 5
  This series includes five scrapbooks containing correspondence, literary productions, and photographs. The scrapbooks give details about Richard Coke and his family, plus other state and local events that occurred while Richard Coke was still active in politics. There is one Gildersleeve photograph preserved in this series. Scrapbooks one through three have been copied onto acid-free paper, while scrapbooks four and five are still in their original binding. The last two scrapbooks contain only photographs.
  - Scrapbook 1 (1 of 12), 1898-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Scrapbook 1 (2 of 12), 1898-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Scrapbook 1 (3 of 12), 1898-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Scrapbook 1 (4 of 12), 1898-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Scrapbook 1 (5 of 12), 1898-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Scrapbook 1 (6 of 12), 1898-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Scrapbook 1 (7 of 12), 1898-1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 1 (8 of 12), 1898-1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 1 (9 of 12), 1898-1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 1 (10 of 12), 1898-1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook 1 (11 of 12), 1898-1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook 1 (12 of 12), 1898-1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook 2 (1 of 7), 1866-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook 2 (2 of 7), 1866-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook 2 (3 of 7), 1866-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook 2 (4 of 7), 1866-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook 2 (5 of 7), 1866-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook 2 (6 of 7), 1866-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook 2 (7 of 7), 1866-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook 3 (1 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook 3 (2 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook 4, undated (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 5, undated (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 5: Loose Materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Photographic Materials, undated; 6
  This series contains several photographs of Richard Coke and several unidentified men. Most of the photographs in this collection are in the scrapbooks series. This
  - Photographs: General, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)